<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Bohemiæ regnum electiuum. That is, A plaine and true relation of the proceeding of the states of Bohemia, from the first foundation of that prouince, by free election of princes and kings vnto Ferdinand the eighteenth King of the house of Austria Wherein is euidently manifested, that the first princes were elected, and no true and simple hereditary succession established, nor practised in all that time, containing about 900. yeares; taken out of vnpartiall and classicque authors.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16295</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 3206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121202</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856387</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856387</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21929</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16295)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21929)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1128:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Bohemiæ regnum electiuum. That is, A plaine and true relation of the proceeding of the states of Bohemia, from the first foundation of that prouince, by free election of princes and kings vnto Ferdinand the eighteenth King of the house of Austria Wherein is euidently manifested, that the first princes were elected, and no true and simple hereditary succession established, nor practised in all that time, containing about 900. yeares; taken out of vnpartiall and classicque authors.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Jones?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Schmid von Schmiedebach, Augustin. Informatio fundamentalis super discursu quodam circa modernum regni Bohemiae statum facto.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>With a printed slip at the foot of B4v supplying an omitted line of type.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Shmid von Schmiedebach, Augustin. --  Informatio fundamentalis super discursu quodam circa modernum regni Bohemiae statum facto --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21929:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21929:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Bohemiae Regnum Electiuum.</hi> THAT IS, A PLAINE AND TRVE RELATION OF the proceeding of the STATES of <hi>BOHEMIA, from the firſt foundation of that</hi> Prouince, by Free Election of <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> vnto FERDINAND the eighteenth King of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN IS EVIDENTLY MANI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted, that the firſt Princes were Elected, and no true and ſimple Hereditary Succeſſion eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <hi>bliſhed, nor practiſed in all that time,</hi> containing about 900. yeares; Taken out of vnpartiall and <hi>Claſsicque Authors.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ESDRAS 1.4.37.38.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>All other things periſh in their vnrighteouſneſſe: But <hi>Truth,</hi> it endureth, and is alwaies ſtrong, it liueth and conquereth for euermore.</p>
            </q>
            <p>MDCXX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:21929:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21929:2"/>
            <head>A PLAINE AND TRVE RELATION OF the proceeding of the States of <hi>BOHEMIA.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Triumph</hi> that I heard ſung aloud of the ſtrength and ſolidneſſe of argument, in a little <hi>Information</hi> ſent abroad almoſt in the darke, to beguile the friends thereof; Maintaining the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> to be ſucceſſiue, and by conſequence rightly deſcended to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> at firſt, ſo farre preiudiced mee, as to thinke ſo much confidence and boldneſſe was ſupported with great probability of truth: And I confeſſe that little pile, as it ſtands com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacted and involued, hath in it ſelfe a faire ſhow, vntill it bee taken in peeces, and ſearched at the Corner Stones. Deſire of mine owne ſatisfaction, firſt made me curious to looke into the beſt <hi>Records</hi> of <hi>Story</hi> of that <hi>Country,</hi> I found the Authors ſuch, as without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for their quality, iudgement, and meanes to know the truth, no diſpaffionate man could refuſe. They doe relate barely what was done and practiſed, without fore-thinking to decide a queſtion, which in their times could not be fore-ſeene, and was the leaſt part of their deſigne; and therefore, their witneſſe, as vn-concerned
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:21929:3"/>therein, is of more authority. When I had informed my ſelfe, I learned of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> to <hi>ſettle my Brethren,</hi> who for want of my leiſure, could not intend ſuch a perplexed ſearch; and might, for zeale and loue of truth, be miſcarried with that which was firſt propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them for truth. I doe not intend to anſwer the <hi>Informato<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> from point to point; but to warne you, that he hath taken aduantages, and forcibly drawne into his purpoſe, fragments and pieces, the whole whereof would be too heauy for his foundation: and as his <hi>ſtuffe</hi> is, ſo are his <hi>vſes</hi> and <hi>applications</hi> wreſted &amp; made crooked, not one grown Timber among them. I haue therfore vndertaken, in a plaine <hi>Narration,</hi> to ſhew the firſt Election of the Princes of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> &amp; the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and practice of <hi>Free Election</hi> vnto <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of <hi>Auſtria:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>34.</hi> from Bre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</hi>
               </note> That not one in all that <hi>ſeries</hi> of ſo manie Princes and Kings did ſucceed in right of Inheritance ſimply; nor did dare ſo to claime an admittance to that <hi>Scepter.</hi> In which diſcourſe I deſire you to conſider, not ſo much the efficacy of euery proofe of Election ſingly (which notwithſtanding is an irrefragable eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence) as the whole file, and thred, purpoſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the States and free people of that Kingdome: for power and affection may ſometimes obſcure and ſlacken the ſtiffneſſe; but yet in euery age and change, more or leſſe, the <hi>right</hi> hath broken forth and ſtood for it ſelfe. I haue not thought it fit to trouble you with latter times, in which the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> hath beene preferred, and haue claimed a ſucceſſion <hi>of right, from a ſucceſsion of Loue,</hi> and ſo haue loſt their beſt title. It is euident in all Electiue kingdomes, that the Sonne of the Father hath beene choſen; for hee was already
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:21929:3"/>ſet vpon the ſtage, and was borne <hi>Candidatus:</hi> So was it often practized in the <hi>Empire,</hi> without preiudice to the right of Election, in any family, when there vvas iuſt cauſe to change. As <hi>Galba</hi> noted of <hi>Auguſtus, Ille in Domo ſucceſſorem quae ſiuit, ego in Republica.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tac. hiſt. lib. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> But if that <hi>Electiue ſucceſsion</hi> be pretended; and an anſwere heere expected I ſay, it is out of my purpoſe, who wade only in the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of former ages, and it is more proper for them to ſatisfie, who can ſearch the <hi>Archiues</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords</hi> of their owne Acts: but for a generall anſwere, we propound, that we dare ioyne iſſue euen in theſe, and be iudged by the <hi>Regiſters</hi> of the publike aſſemblies vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on euery Election, and by the <hi>Defeſall</hi> and <hi>Reuerſall</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters giuen by thoſe Princes of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> their own Acts, acknowledging the free Election and good will of the States of <hi>Bohemia, ſine vlla alia obligatione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To lay our owne foundation ſure and conſpicuous, I firſt preſent this definition of a <hi>Kingdome ſucceſsiue;</hi> That the <hi>Crowne,</hi> and all the <hi>Rights</hi> of <hi>Regality,</hi> doe <hi>de Iure</hi> deſcend vnto the next <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Princeſſe</hi> of the bloud <hi>Royall</hi> in right Line; And that it is as great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption of <hi>ſucceſsion</hi> that a <hi>younger Houſe</hi> bee prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as that a <hi>Stranger;</hi> and that the <hi>States</hi> and people haue no right to put by or refuſe the next in bloud vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any pretence: and theſe rules eſtabliſh and limit a Kingdome <hi>ſucceſsiue.</hi> But that this <hi>Canon</hi> hath neuer taken place, nor beene practiſed by the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> I ſhew in theſe fiue Concluſions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the firſt Princes of <hi>Bohemia</hi> were Elected, and the forme of their Election recorded.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the practice of Election hath continued ſo, that the Yonger Brethren haue beene preferred before
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21929:4"/>the Elder, the Vncle before the Nephew, ſonne to the elder brother: the Coſen of the yonger Houſe, before Coſen of the elder: the Husband of the yonger ſiſter, before the Husband of the elder.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Meere ſtangers before daughters and ſiſters of the laſt Kings, and before any of the Bloud.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The power and practice of depoſition or reiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in caſe of miſgouernment, or want of due <hi>Forme</hi> in <hi>Election.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. That almoſt all the Kings that haue immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſucceeded their Fathers, haue beene Elected and Crowned during the Fathers life, or choſen Marqueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Morauia</hi> (a ſtep to the Crowne) by the authority of the Father in poſſeſſion, or for his merit and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory dead: ſo that no ſuch ſucceſſion hath been pure <hi>de Iure,</hi> but ayded and grounded vpon other rights then of ſucceſſion. All which examples and Rules doe diametrally oppugne and ouerthrow the pretence of <hi>Hereditary Succeſsion,</hi> and conſequently proue (for there) is not one Prince without the reach of one of theſe Rules) <hi>Bohemiae Regnum eſſe Electinum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Crocus</hi> after <hi>Zechius,</hi> who ſetled his Colonies in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> was made there Iudge by the people for his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue;<note place="margin">Geor. Barthold. Boh pia pag. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Crocus vir Iuſtus, &amp; magnae apud Bohemos, tunc tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris opinionis &amp; authoritatis, princeps dilectus eſt: vir hic fuit Iudiciorum in deliberatione diſcretus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coſm. Prag. Chron. pag. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ad quem, tam de proprijs tribubus, quam ex totius prouinciae plebtbus, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut apes ad alueria, ita omnes ad dirimenda conuolabant Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Crocus</hi> had three daughters, <hi>Kari</hi> eldeſt, <hi>Tethka</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Luboſſa</hi> third and yongeſt.<note place="margin">Coſm. Prag. pag. <hi>4.5 6.</hi>
               </note> This laſt for her wiſe dome was by the people choſen a Princeſſe, or Iudge;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21929:4"/>There fell out a controuerſie betweene two <hi>Bohemians</hi> about the limits of their ground, which <hi>Luboſſa</hi> ended by ſentence; The party diſpleaſed and condemned, being enraged, renounced the Iudgement, diſdaining it from that ſexe; and thereby tooke occaſion to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand a man to gouerne. <hi>Luboſſa</hi> was vnwilling to let goe the Reynes, and firſt threatens what and how vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent the dominion of man would proue,<note place="margin">Geor. Birtbold. pag. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> after diſſwades by force of many arguments; <hi>Ad haec vulgus confuſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ult at clamore, omnes vno ore Ducem ſibi poſcunt dari,</hi> which when ſhe could not auoyd, ſhe cunningly propounds a free Election, by letting looſe an horſe that ſhould ſtay before a man eating at an Iron table, which was agreed vnto; and then ſhe ſayes, <hi>Ite demum, vt quem vos cras e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligatis in Dominum, ego aſſumam mihi in maritum.</hi> This horſe ſtood ſtill before <hi>Primiſlaus,</hi> who was eating his dinner vpon his plough ſhare, and ſo he is choſen;<note place="margin">The firſt form of Election. <hi>Coſm. Prag. p.</hi> 6.</note> and the forme of Election recorded to bee by ſalutation of all the people; they all all cry out, <hi>Domina noſtra Luboſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, &amp; plebs vniuerſa mandant vt cito venias &amp;c. te Ducem te Iudicem, te Rectorem, te Protectorem te ſolum nobis in Dominum eligimus;</hi> Here are three Elections in the firſt foundation, and one Reiection of <hi>Luboſſa</hi> confirmed, and the forme recorded.</p>
            <p>To wade deeper into the firſt times, is vnneſſary; onely one obſeruation of <hi>Coſma Pragenſis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brau li. <hi>7.</hi> pag. <hi>54.</hi> an. <hi>1002.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Vlricus</hi> the eighteenth Prince, who had no iſſue by lawfull marriage, ſaw by chance at a Well a handſome maide waſhing, named <hi>Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>na,</hi> vpon whom he caſt affection, and begat a ſonne called <hi>Breceſlaus: Vlricus</hi> had put out his brother <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irs</hi> eyes, yet hee tooke his Nephew, before whom hee was in right of bloud, and preſented
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:21929:5"/>him <hi>adſedem principalem, &amp; ſitut ſemper in electione ducis faciunt, &amp;c.</hi> which proues hee was Elected, and the continuation of Election declared in thoſe words, <hi>ſicut ſemper in Electione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To proceed to times better knowne, and to an eſtate better ſetled, and to looke downward from <hi>Breciſlaus</hi> the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Prince, or as <hi>Coſma Prag:</hi> the ninteenth of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia,</hi> we ſhall finde no ſucceſſion from Father to Son, nor from Brother to Brother regular, but the fitteſt to gouerne, or the beſt beloued, euer choſen by the <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians. Breciſlaus</hi> had fiue ſonnes, <hi>Spitigneus</hi> 1: <hi>Vratiſlaus</hi> 2: <hi>Conradus</hi> 3: <hi>Otho</hi> 4: <hi>Iaromirus</hi> 5. <hi>Spitigneus</hi> the eldeſt ſucceeded, but by Election vpon recommendation of his Father.<note place="margin">Coſm. Prag. pag. <hi>30.</hi> an. <hi>1055</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Poſt Breciſlai obitum filium eius primogenitum, nomine Spignen, omnes Bohemiae gentes, magni &amp; parui, communi Conſilio, &amp; voluntate pari elegunt ſibi in Ducem, cantantes kyrieleizon.</hi> After his death, <hi>Vratiſlaus</hi> his brother was choſen,<note place="margin">pag. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>omnibus Boemis fauentibus:</hi> He had alſo ſixe ſonnes; <hi>Breceſlaus</hi> 1: <hi>Boleſlaus</hi> 2: <hi>Boriuorius</hi> 3: <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> 4: <hi>Sobieſlaus</hi> 5: <hi>Henricus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Olmunts</hi> 6: All theſe ſhould haue ſucceeded the Father in rule of ſucceſſion, but <hi>Conradus</hi> the Vncle was choſen Duke; Hee had two ſonnes, <hi>Vdalricus,</hi> or as <hi>Coſma Prag:</hi> calls him, <hi>Oalricus</hi> and <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> or <hi>Lutoldus:</hi> Now, in true ſucceſſion, one of theſe muſt ſucceed the Father <hi>Conrad:</hi> but now the <hi>Bohemians</hi> returne to <hi>Breciſlaus</hi> their Coſin German, and eldeſt ſonne to <hi>Vratiſlaus;</hi> and yet they returne not to him as in right,<note place="margin">Dubran. p. <hi>78.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nam diu ambigebant or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines, num Brecislaum ab exilio adregnum paternum reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carent, an domi aliquem ex fratribus eius qui regnaret:</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of <hi>Breciſlaus.</hi> they againe skippe his three ſonnes, <hi>Vladiſlaus, Henricus,</hi> and <hi>Theobaldus,</hi> who ſhould
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21929:5"/>ſucceed, and alſo the next elder brother, and <hi>Boriuerius</hi> the yonger is choſen: Now <hi>Vdalricus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coſm. Prag. pag. <hi>54.55.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>Oalritus</hi> the firſt ſonne of <hi>Conrad,</hi> thinkes himſelfe wronged to bee twice neglected in the Election; and complaines to the Emperour at <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> ſollicits him, by prayers, by friends, by money, to helpe him to the kingdome poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by his Cozen <hi>Borinoy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubran. pag. <hi>84:</hi> Ibid.</note> The Emperour takes his money, and lends him ſome ſuccors, <hi>Sed hac conditione, vt liberum ſit Bohemis, aut Vdalricu, at Boriuorium, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere Principem; vtrum videlicet borum magis idoneum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilemque approbauerint:</hi> But when it came to a declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to what end hee would vſe theſe aydes, to clayme the kingdome by right, hee dares not, but enterprets himſelfe, <hi>Dat ſibi Dncatus inſignia &amp; vexillum,</hi> (which were due to him by bloud, had hee beene the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt of the family) <hi>Sed in Ducem elegendi obtentum ponit in arbitrio Bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>horum:</hi> But the <hi>Bohemians</hi> refuſe his claime made by his Embaſſadors, and adhere to their firſt Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Boriuoy,</hi> and defeat <hi>Oalricus</hi> and all his preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in battaile. <hi>Boriuoy</hi> had a ſonne called <hi>Iaromirus,</hi> who ſhould haue ſucceeded, had that right taken place: but <hi>Suatopulcus</hi> gets in by fauour, and by the relapſe of the people depoſeth <hi>Boriuoy:</hi> This man was Cozen German to <hi>Boriuoy,</hi> of a younger houſe, the ſonne of <hi>Othe,</hi> the fourth ſonne of <hi>Breciſlaus</hi> the two and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth. This <hi>Suatopulcus</hi> was not long after reiected, &amp; <hi>Borinoy</hi> againe receined: And hee againe the ſecond time depoſed and thruſt out, and <hi>Suatopulcus</hi> reſtored; &amp; ſo continued Prince to his death. He had a ſon called <hi>Henry,</hi> baptized by the Emperour,<note place="margin">Coſm. Prag. pag. <hi>57.</hi>
               </note> and brought vp by him; yet hee being ſlaine in the Campe, <hi>Othoniger</hi> his brother was Elected Prince. The Emperor comming
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21929:6"/>to ſee and lament the dead body of <hi>Suatopulcus,</hi> and to appeaſe the people, who it ſeemes feared leſt he would obtrude vpon them a Succeſſor againſt their will,<note place="margin">Pag. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantibus immenſis Boemis conceſsit, vt quemcunque volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſent, ſuorum ex filijs principum ſibi in Ducem cligerent.</hi> There was the Sonne of <hi>Suatopulcus</hi> aliue, (for any thing appeares) many of the grand-children of <hi>Vra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſlaus</hi> the firſt King, and foure and twentieth Prince, before <hi>Otho</hi> in the right of Succeſſion, yet <hi>Weſeck</hi> of <hi>Morauia</hi> intercedes that he may be choſen Duke; him alſo <hi>Henry</hi> the Emperour fauours, before the ſonne and his owne God-ſonne, and the people being moſt <hi>Morauians</hi> approue the Election, and preſently in the Campe admit him for their Prince, crying <hi>Kyrieleyzon,</hi> and in foure daies brought him to <hi>Prage,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. pag. <hi>90.</hi>
               </note> at which <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brauius</hi> ſayes, the Bohemians tooke offence. <hi>Queſti ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt de electione in Caſtris factâ, contra Maiorum Inſtituta, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remque veterem:</hi> And <hi>Coſma Pragenſis</hi> ſayes, he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed as he was,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quod quia ſine conſenſu Boemorum &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopi, efficere conabantur, fruſtratur eorum temeritus, &amp; Sacramenta olim exhibita in medio conſilio recitantur:</hi> And <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> the brother of <hi>Boreuoy</hi> was Elected, <hi>vt Iura Principatus, Iure adoptata,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Coſm. Prag. pag. <hi>60.</hi>
               </note> (that is by lawfull Election) <hi>omnibus aſcentientibus obtineret.</hi> This <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> was younger brother to <hi>Boreuoy</hi> long ſince depoſed, and now hee complaines; and <hi>Otho</hi> the brother of <hi>Suato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcos</hi> renewes a pretence: Firſt, <hi>Boreuoy</hi> treates by his Embaſſadors, to perſwade his yonger Brother to reſigne; <hi>Reſponſom huic a Vladiſlao huiuſmodi retulit, non eſſe rem priuatam quam Boriuorius peteret,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. p. 91.</note> 
               <hi>ſed ad vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſi populi ſuffragium illam pertinere; proin haud ab vno fratre, ſed ab omnibus ordinibus principatum eſſe ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum:</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:21929:6"/>The Bohemians adhere truely to their owne Election, ouerthrew <hi>Otho</hi> in Battaile,<note place="margin">Coſm. Prag. pag. <hi>62.</hi>
               </note> and after <hi>Vla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus</hi> by the Emperours deliuery gets <hi>Boreuoy</hi> into his power, and all his friends: Hee dyes, and <hi>Sobieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> his yongeſt brother is choſen. <hi>Otho niger</hi> againe pretends, <hi>quia aetate prior eſſet,</hi> but is reiected. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bieſlaus</hi> had foure ſonnes, <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> the firſt,<note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>9<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sobieſlaus</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Vdalricus</hi> the third, <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the fourth. Theſe ſhould haue ſucceeded the Father if ſucceſſion had preuailed, but <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> his Nephew, the ſonne of his Brother <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> (euen by the fauor of <hi>Sobieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus</hi> his Vncle againſt his owne Children, and by the Emperors helpe) was deſigned Prince of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and by the Emperor crowned the ſecond King: But the Bohemians, becauſe hee was yonger in yeares then <hi>Conrad</hi> his Cozen Germane the ſonne of <hi>Leopold,</hi> ſon of <hi>Otho.</hi> And becauſe his Election was not formall,<note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ac Caeſaris potius quam Boemorum Principem quando non in Bohemia ſed in curia Caeſaris Princeps ſit creatus, Throno deijciunt, &amp; in locum eius Conradum ſubſtituunt:</hi> But the Emperour <hi>Fredericke</hi> fauouring <hi>Vladislaus,</hi> reſtor'd him by force, and his ſonne <hi>Fredericke</hi> ſucceeded, but was after alſo expulſed, and <hi>Vdalricus</hi> the third ſonne of <hi>Sobieslaus</hi> the 30th Prince choſen, his elder brethren being neglected; He was Cozen German halfe remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from <hi>Fredericke;</hi> He dying, his next elder brother <hi>Sobieslaus</hi> ſucceeded, and now <hi>Fredericke</hi> had againe gotten poſſeſſion, &amp; was againe expulled: After which <hi>Conradus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Leopold</hi> forenamed, was a new declared Prince of Bohemia, <hi>ſuffragijs primorum or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. P. 126.</note> 
               <hi>Fredericke</hi> was againe reſtored, and <hi>Conrad</hi> expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and then <hi>Fredericke</hi> dying, though hee had fower
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21929:7"/>brethren aliue, <hi>Albert, Suatopulk, Premiſlans,</hi> and <hi>Vla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus,</hi> which ſhould all haue taken place in true ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. <hi>Conradus</hi> was in his abſence declared Prince <hi>ab ordinibus Bohemia;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>130.</hi>
               </note> After his death, <hi>Venceſlans</hi> the ſon of <hi>Otho niger,</hi> younger brother to <hi>Suatopulcus</hi> his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, but preferred before many neerer the Succeſſion, was Elected Prince. Him <hi>Primiſlaus</hi> expulſed, but fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his returne, hee quitted <hi>Prage;</hi> And <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> in his returne died, leauing a Sonne called <hi>Spitigneus va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cante principali ſede, Henricus</hi> (the ſecond Sonne of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſlaus</hi> the ſixe and twentieth Biſhop of <hi>Prage</hi>) <hi>diem co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiorum habendorum Praga indicit,<note place="margin">Dubrau. P. <hi>132.</hi>
                  </note> candida tumque in illo principatus pro ſpitigenio pupillo agit: Boemi parumper deliberantes, ipſum Henricum vnanimi aſſenſu, magnaque voce, Principem Boemiae pronuntiant:</hi> Heere alſo was a ſucceſſion interrupted by the free Election, not onely <hi>Spitigneus</hi> the ſonne of the laſt <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> reiected be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a childe, but <hi>Henry</hi> preferred before all the Sons of <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> the ſecond King of <hi>Bohemia: Henry</hi> not long after falls ſicke, and aſſembles all the Nobility, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring vnto them his deſire to reſigne the Principality of <hi>Bohemia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubr. u p. <hi>134.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dat<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ill is poteſtatem eligendi Principis quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque voluerint:</hi> but the <hi>Bohemians</hi> hoping on his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couery would not proceed to a new Election, and ſo he remained Prince to his death. Being dead, <hi>de ſucceſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne in comitijs ab ordinibus variatum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>135.</hi>
               </note> at laſt they Elected <hi>Vladiſlaus,</hi> yonger brother to <hi>Primiſlaus,</hi> once before in poſſeſſion, and fift ſonne of <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> the ſecond King: two elder Brethren at leaſt aliue: He reſigned in fiue moneths to <hi>Primiſlaus</hi> his brother, who was Elected Prince,<note place="margin">Dubr. Genealog. Page 139.</note> being of the ſecond venter, by the <hi>Landgraues</hi> daughter, and his elder brethren and their children,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21929:7"/>for any thing appeares, being refuſed: And this <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſlaus</hi> was crowned the third King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> by the Emperour <hi>Philip</hi> at <hi>Mentz, de omnium quae aderant ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia, Anno</hi> 1199.</p>
            <p>Thus it is euident from <hi>Bretiſlaus</hi> the 22. to this <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſlaus Ottocarus</hi> the thirtieth, in which are ſeuenteene changes, <hi>no kinde of ſucceſsion</hi> hath taken place, but that the yonger brother that beene preferred before the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the vncle before the Nephew, the yonger houſe before the elder, and many Princes depoſed for miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gouernment, or want of forme in true election.</p>
            <p>After <hi>Primiſlaus,</hi> foure Kings are pretended to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the ſeauenth King: But <hi>Primiſlaus</hi> cauſeth his ſonne <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> to be crowned in his life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time, and <hi>Dubrauius</hi> notes it,<note place="margin">pag. <hi>139.</hi>
               </note> that he was carefull of his owne houſe, <hi>Exin rebus ſuis domi intentas, Venceslaum ſilium, etiamſi puerum, regem coronat,</hi> which hee needed not haue done, had he <hi>Ius ſucceſsionis,</hi> and was eaſie for him to doe, being in poſſeſſion. When hee died, his friends concealed it, and his ſonne <hi>Ottocarus</hi> entred with an army, and ſo was admitted.<note place="margin">Idem <hi>157.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Propter frequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam comitatus, qui eum ex Austria Styria, Morauia comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabantur; ita pleriſque metuendus quia armatus vener at;</hi> Hee was Marqueſſe of <hi>Morauia,</hi> eſtabliſhed in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers life time, and becauſe hee was not then admitted to the Crowne by Election, it ſeemes he entred armed, which hee needed not doe to his Inheritance: He was ſlaine in the battell of <hi>Laua,</hi> and his ſonne <hi>Venceſlaus,</hi> a Childe was admitted in his Infancy in honour of the Father, <hi>ex conſenſu omnium Ordinum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem <hi>16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>cura fouendi illius ad Marchionem Brandeburgum:</hi> The Marqueſſe abuſeth the truſt, and carries him away: At 15. yeares of age,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21929:8"/>he is reſtored to the Bohemians for a ſumme of mony, not till now, was he choſen King, which I inferre out of <hi>Dubranius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem <hi>169.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Inter catera ab omnibus acclamantum eſt, Adueniſti tandem deſiderabilis, quem tam diu ex pectaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Ottogari ô inclytaproles,</hi> (which inſinuates the loue of the father) <hi>nihil videlicet tum Otthogari nomine clarius, nihil ad conciliandum omnium ordinem fauorem efficacius:</hi> which implyes the Election by the States, although the reaſon be rendred why they choſe him, for loue of the father, yet ſtill their fauour was the formall part of his admiſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the 7.<note place="margin">The ſtories mention not the manner his Admiſsion.</note> King ſucceeded the Father, &amp; in him ended the ancient Race of their Princes; in all theſe, no ſucceſſion of right eſtabliſhed. He had 3. ſiſters, <hi>Iudith</hi> eldeſt, <hi>Anne</hi> &amp; <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> the firſt married to <hi>Rupertus</hi> of <hi>Naſſau</hi> the Emperors ſon; the ſecond to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthia,</hi> the third yet a maid.<note place="margin">Dubrau p. <hi>179.</hi>
               </note> The States aſſemble in the Biſhop of <hi>Prages</hi> houſe, <hi>ad ius comitioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſumma<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione de Rege eligendo certant, alijs perigrinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> regem penitus aſpernantibus, alijs inter Rodulphum Caeſaris Alberti filiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; Henricum ex Carinthia qui praeſens aderat, variantibus:</hi> as yet no mention make of any right in the daughters: <hi>Tobias Bechinus,</hi> who fauoured the ſtrangers, ſons of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> to croſſe the aduerſe party who would not accept them, ſaith, <hi>Quando non alium Regem quam Boemum creare libet, Regia<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> progenies in Boemia planê deficiat reuert amur ad Pagum ſtadium, vnde Primiſlaus ex ruſtico, priamus in Boemia factus eſt Princeps atque indidem, nos quoque Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem nobis adciſcamus:</hi> Yet that was not his deſire, but onely to diuert the Election, which vtterly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes the pretended Contract with the houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria;</hi> for hee being of that party, ſhould haue pleaded
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21929:8"/>it, if he had knowne it, or had thought it of force, &amp; not haue returned to an <hi>originall Election,</hi> which fully anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hilated the Contract, but it ſeems <hi>Tobias</hi> knew nothing of it: And ſo hee alſo reiects the ſiſters, for that was his end, eſteeming them no heyres, though they were <hi>ex progeniê Regia,</hi> &amp; concluded they might lawfully elect a ſtranger in bloud. This motion was reiected, not that they might elect a ſtranger, but becauſe the other ſide vnderſtood his craft, that he would obtrude a German, hatefull to the Bohemians: and ſo he was commanded without further Prefaces, to nominate one in a faire E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection: He as Chamberlayne of Boheme, prefers firſt <hi>Rodolph,</hi> and then his brother <hi>Fredericke,</hi> ſonnes of <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert, Quo audito, Cruſsina Lychtemburgus, Quouſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tandem, inquit, nobis ingeres tuos Germanos Regum noſtrorum par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricidas, nec plura locutus, ſtringit gladium, &amp; Thobiam transfodit:</hi> The next day, the two ſiſters, <hi>Anna</hi> marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Carinthia, Elizabeth</hi> a maid come into the Court, not as heyres, <hi>or ant ve ſui haberi rationem, ne velut ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enae a Regno praetereantur.</hi> And <hi>Henry</hi> the Husband of <hi>Anne</hi> vvas choſen King, but he could not hold it; for the Emperour ſtood for his Sonne, not by a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, but as preuayling in Election, and vpon that onely grounds his Title to place him by force, <hi>Caefare alacriter, inſtante, ne filius ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns, qui priores partes in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragijs tulerat, poſteriores in Regno acquirendo ferret.</hi> He enters Bohemia vvith an Army, <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Carinthia,</hi> and his wife giue way, and ſo he fortifies the election of <hi>Rodolph,</hi> and Crownes him, a meere ſtranger in bloud or other title, but the Election pretended. <hi>Rodolph</hi> dies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dubrauius</hi> ree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons <hi>Fredoricke</hi> as elected, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe not.</note> and <hi>Henrie</hi> of <hi>Carinthia</hi> returnes with his Wife; In which <hi>interim,</hi> the Emperour endeuors the Election of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21929:9"/>
               <hi>Fredericke</hi> his ſecond ſonne, but is ſlaine before hee could effect it, and then theſe were receiued with great Ioy; After three or foure yeares the <hi>Bohemians</hi> grew weary of <hi>Henries</hi> gouernment, and ſent Ambaſſadors to <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Luxenburgh</hi> then Emperor, to ſend his ſonne <hi>Iohn</hi> to marry <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the yonger ſiſter to <hi>Anne,</hi> and <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the ſeuenth, and that they would elect him King. The Emperor accepts it, and married <hi>Iohn</hi> at <hi>Spire:</hi> The <hi>Bohemians</hi> depoſed <hi>Henry</hi> for ill gouernment, as <hi>Bartoldus</hi> notes,<note place="margin">Geor. Barthold. pag. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hunc Boemi ſibi Regem deligunt, ſed quia male adminiſtrauit, miſerune ad Caeſarem, Henricum ſextum, Legatos ſuos:</hi> So was <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Luxenburgh</hi> Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, a ſtranger alſo in bloud; for he could pretend no right by his wife in Succeſſion, <hi>Anne</hi> the elder ſiſter li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. Concerning the contract made betweene <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heme</hi> and <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the elder ſtories ſpeake nothing of it. <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> declared not the pretence,<note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>180.</hi>
               </note> but ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens the Election of his owne ſonnes by making a fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by mariage of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the widdow of <hi>Venceſlaus.</hi> And <hi>Hieronimo Canini</hi> in his hiſtory of the Election of the Roman Kings,<note place="margin">Hieron. Canini. pag. <hi>211.</hi>
               </note> cites, that ſuch an accord was made, That for want of heyres in eyther Houſe, the other ſhould ſucceed; but withall notes, <hi>Encore que le Royaume ſoyt a l'Election des Barons, &amp; des ſeigneurs du pays:</hi> which beeing cleerely confeſſed, an accord made betweene them for their owne aduantage, to the preiudice of the freedome of <hi>Bohemia</hi> could not be auaileable, nor was euer confirmed by practice in ſucceſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Luxenburgh</hi> is choſen, and is a great Prince, he begins indeed to ſeeke to eſtabliſh the Kingdome in his <hi>Lyne,</hi> and in his life-time practiſeth to exchange it with <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of <hi>Bauare,</hi> which it is like he affected,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21929:9"/>to leaue them to the fortune of Election, which is a <hi>taeite</hi> confeſſion of the right in the States to Elect: when it was reuealed to the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> they tooke it in ſo ill part, that hee ſhould by a ſecret practice infringe their liberty, or ſeeme to haue right, to obtrude a King vpon them at his choyce, that they almoſt reuolted againſt him, and would not be reconciled, vntill a copy of the treaty was ſhewed, that he did nothing, but with reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the conſent of the States to confirme it. The words of <hi>Dubrauiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> are conſiderable.<note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>193.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sed longè omnium maximu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> odiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi ab omnibus or dinibus conflauit, inchoatâ cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lodonico permutatione, qua regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pro Bauariae principatu commutare voluit, At Boemi in deteriorem partem inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretati funt, quaſi illos Rex vendere Germanis, &amp; prodcre cuperet: Ergo omnes in vnum conſpirant, vt pereant potius quam non perdant illos, qui ad exitium Patriae corum immi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neant: At que haec turba maior viſa, quam vt pacart vel ipſo rege praeſente potuerit, &amp; niſi pacata eſſet, ſpes de retinendo ei regno decollabat:</hi> So that this feare of <hi>Iohn,</hi> confeſſeth a forfeiture, and a power to depoſe him, and then hee procures the Emperor to come in perſon to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> where at the towne of <hi>Luticium</hi> the Emperor thus excuſes the King. <hi>Illic in maxima Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morum frequentia, Regem illorum de tam graui ſuſpitione, qualem de illo haberent, teſtimonio ſuo expurgat; pactionem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que illis, quam cum Rege inire caeperat, ſcriptum oſtendit, in qua diſerte aperteque appoſitum erat, ita illa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ratam &amp; fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam fore ſi communi Bohemorum aſſenſu confirmata fuerit.</hi> So iealous were they then of their right, that nothing could appeaſe them, but the ſight of his owne agnition of the validity of their conſent in transferring the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: <hi>Iohn</hi> cauſed his ſonne <hi>Charles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. P. <hi>201.</hi>
               </note> to bee admitted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21929:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Morauia</hi> in his life time, an halfe electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in the Empire the King of Romans, and a ſtep to the kingdome; And indeed he was ſo fauoured of the Bohemians for his valour, witte, and skill in tongues, that his admittance was eaſily procured; yea hee was ſo fauoured of the Bohemians,<note place="margin">Idem <hi>202.</hi>
               </note> that his Father ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and feared him: Soone after hee was choſen King of the Romanes at <hi>Bon,</hi> and now it was not eaſie for the Bohemians to refuſe him if they would, for he preuai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in vniuerſall loue: <hi>Charles</hi> in his life laboured all he could to ſettle the Kingdome in his iſſue, and to that end in confirming the priuiledges of <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Emperour, inſerts a Clauſe of expoſition to his owne aduantage, which cannot extend beyond the Text: But 8. yeeres after, eſtabliſhing the ſucceſſion of all the Electors, he expects expreſſely the Kingdome of Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, and the free Election of the States,<note place="margin">Onuphirus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Bulla. p. <hi>431.</hi>
               </note> not when the heyres royall ſhould faile (as they pretend) but vvhen the Crowne ſhall be vacant, <hi>quemcunque voluerunt,</hi> as is notorious in <hi>Bulla aurea;</hi> His ſonne <hi>Venceſlaus</hi> was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, but he gouerned ill, and left the kingdome in trouble by the <hi>Huſsites</hi> and <hi>Ziſca.</hi> After 12 years, <hi>Sigiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mund</hi> his brother enters by force,<note place="margin">Dubrau. p. 243.</note> the kingdom weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and torne in peeces by ciuill diſſention, &amp; takes the Crown: and hauing only one daughter <hi>Elizabeth</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Geor. Barthold. pag. <hi>29.</hi> AEn. Syl. p. <hi>54</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> on his death-bedde conuocates the States, takes care for the election, &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents <hi>Albert</hi> his ſonne in Law: <hi>Albertum Auſtriae Ducem generum ſuum eſſe &amp; virtute praeſtantem, &amp; gener is nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate ſublimem cum ſe non minus amare quam filium, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſorem itaque ſuum nominare, rogare ſupremam volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſuam exequantur: beatum id regnum fore, vbi
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21929:10"/>Albertus imperauer it,</hi> Here are reaſons of conuenience, of Nobility, of Vertue, and hee nominates a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor to their choyce, which he could not doe, nor they refuſe, if <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his daughter ſhould ſucceed in right; and ſo <hi>Albert</hi> is choſen, a ſtranger in bloud.<note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>266.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Albert</hi> hath 3. children, <hi>Ladiſlaus Paſtunus</hi> was admitted King, but he was a Childe, and therefore the States offered the Kingdome to <hi>Albert</hi> of Bauaria, hee refuſeth it vpon Conditions of Religion, <hi>That hee would not be bound to admitte the Chalice in the Sacrament, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired,</hi> not conſidering at all the right of <hi>Ladiſlaus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> Then they offer it to <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Emperour as Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor; but among the Ambaſſadors, <hi>Ptaſco,</hi> no friend to <hi>Albertus</hi> father of <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> perſwades the Emperor to make himſelfe King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as the firſt of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria:</hi> but he refuſeth both the ones Counſell, and the generall offer of <hi>Tutorſhip,</hi> and recommits it wholly to the <hi>Bohemians,</hi> as hauing beſt vnderſtanding and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in their owne affaires. In this <hi>Interraigne, Podiebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> conſults of calling home <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> now in the hands of <hi>Fredericke,</hi> for it ſeemes eyther he bredd him,<note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>271:</hi>
               </note> or was retired to him: and after deliberation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes to receiue him vpon conditions; and at his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance they giue him the oath,<note place="margin">Ibid. <hi>272.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quo praeſtito capita dein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de libertatum ab omnibus ordinibus miſſa exhibet,</hi> &amp;c. Hee dyes vvithout Iſſue, and leaues two ſiſters, <hi>Anne</hi> the Eldeſt, married to <hi>William</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxe, Elizabeth</hi> to <hi>Caſsimer</hi> King of <hi>Poland. Ladiſlaus</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding himſelfe ſtroken with Death, calls <hi>Podiebradius,</hi> and foreſeeing in the affections of the Bohemians who ſhould be Elected,<note place="margin">Georg. Bartold, pag. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> neuer thinkes of his ſiſters as in any right, nor once mentions them, but <hi>mihi moriendum eſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21929:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:21929:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21929:12"/>Regnum in tua manuerit, Duo te peto, vti prouinciales iuſte regas</hi> &amp;c. <hi>alterum, vt qui me ſecuti ſunt ex Auſtria, caeteriſque prouincijs in Patriam ſuam inuiolatos remittas. Podiebradius</hi> modeſtly ſeemes to decline it, excuſeth and hopes the King ſhal recouer, neuer, for a Complement, once mentions any heyre, ſiſter, or kinred of the King, which he could not in manners doe, nor with ſafety o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, if they had had right, and the King who ſhould maintaine their Intereſt yet aliue: But <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> ſets his eyes onely vpon <hi>Podiebrad, Promitte quod cupio, nam me mori certum est: Ladiſlaus</hi> eyes, and <hi>Podibradius</hi> beeing Gouernour, calls the Aſſembly for Election: The French King ſtands a meere ſtranger in bloud, and his Ambaſſadors come to <hi>Prage;</hi> but becauſe they vvere vnwilling to admit a ſtranger, they reſolued to finiſh the Election, before the French had audience. The manner of the Election is recorded by <hi>Dubrauius,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially; <hi>Locus eligendo Regi in domo Praetoria veteris vrbis conſtitutus,</hi> where, after firſt ſolemnely going to the Church, <hi>Rokickzanus</hi> makes an Oration to perſwade them not to looke vpon any Stranger nor Germane: Among themſelues, he firſt propounds the Gouernor <hi>Podiebradius,</hi> whoſe Armes had defended their Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; or if they diſliked him, and thought no <hi>Bohemian</hi> eminent enough, nor worthy of ſo high aduancement, he counſells a new way of gouernment, vtterly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh a Monarchy: <hi>Aut hunc Regem eſſe nominandum aut ſi nemo inter Boemos tanto faſtigio dignus cenſeatur, Haebreo more duodecim Iudicis aſſumendos, qui Populum Boemum aequo Iure gubernarent. Hinc in Praetorium itum, &amp; tam foris, quam intus prius acclamantum quam decretu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> VIVAT REX GEORGIVS: Here is a ſolemn Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21929:12"/>on, and therein a propoſition to change the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men into <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> and laſtly a ſtranger in bloud to the Crowne of Bohemia Elected, the daughters and ſiſters of the two laſt Kings not once in queſtion: And <hi>George</hi> held the Crowne of Bohemia to his death, and this Election and Coronation of <hi>George</hi> was confirmed by <hi>Calixtus</hi> the Pope, which no Auſſrian dare ſay hee would haue done in iniury of the true heyre or their Houſe. <hi>George Podiebrad</hi> had three ſonnes,<note place="margin">Idem <hi>281.</hi>
               </note> two liued at his death, yet in his laſt meditations hee durſt not once caſt his eyes vpon any of them; His words are,<note place="margin">Idem <hi>289.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nollem autem, quantum in me ſitum eſt, libenter committere</hi> (which implies he had no intereſt in deſigning an heyre, but by way of Counſayle) <hi>vt poſt obitum meum, ipſum Regnum in aliquod diſerimen adduceretur propter dubium regni ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſorem, proin ſcire aueo, quidn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in hac cauſa agere, quem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uè Regem vobis legare deſtinaneritis; Reſpondentibus nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam ipſo Rege ſu perſtite ſucceſſoris faciendam eſſe mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem</hi> (perhaps to preuent the preiudice, iealous to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue their right entire) <hi>inſtabat auidus, donec ab ill it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torqueret, non adme dum ſibi gratam ſententiam, qua ſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerent ſentire, apud Polonos Regem eſſe quaerendum, cum quibus &amp; linguae &amp; moribus non multùm diſſentirent.</hi> They expreſſe their reaſons for likeneſſe of manners, and language, without any mentioning a right by the ſecond daughter of <hi>Albert,</hi> which they could not doe without iniury to <hi>Anne</hi> the Elder ſiſter married to <hi>Saxe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Podebradius</hi> with this anſwer was diſmaid, for thogh he durſt not expreſſe it, hee had ſtrong hopes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes for his owne ſonnes; but knowing the right of free Election, and hauing diſcouered their affections;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21929:13"/>in the little pauſe hee had of life, neuer ſought to alter the Inclination of the Bohemians, but prouided onely to leaue his ſonnes rich, and poſſeſſing them with the mooueables of the Kingdome, commanded them to retire to the Caſtle of <hi>Podiebrad.</hi> A ſolemne Parliament is held for the Election, <hi>Matthias</hi> King of Hungarie ſtands, and is ready to threaten vvith an Army, and hath a party in Bohemia, therefore they remooue the Seſſion, <hi>ad montes Cuthenſes, data omnibus fide publica, vt quiſque ad illa libere veniret &amp; rediret, ſummaque cum libertate ſuffragia perageret.</hi> Three great men in Bohemia declare for <hi>Matthias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. P. <hi>290.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>contentiſsimâ ſuffragatione, ſed maior numerus Vladiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laum Caſsimiri Poloniae Regis filium, etiamnum adoleſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem nullarumque partium factionibus per aetatem infec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, Regem poſſebant, numeroque praenaluerunt: Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias</hi> ſtirres, enters with an Army, and moleſteth <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Emperour in Auſtria and Styria, and partly thereby, partly by promiſe of money, procures an Inveſtiture, Although hee had formerly granted it to <hi>Vladiſlaus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Caſsimere</hi> of Poland, yet the Bohemians maintaine their Election, and repulſe <hi>Matthias,</hi> heere is no reaſon of bloud, but fitneſſe, in reſpect of partialitie, mentioned in the Election: And if reaſon of bloud could then haue been vrged, <hi>Anne,</hi> or <hi>VVilliam</hi> of Saxe, or their Iſſue muſt haue preceded, and by Conſequence, now the Elector of <hi>Brandeburgh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lodouicus</hi> his ſonne ſucceded, but was admitted and Crowned at three yeares of age, by his Fathers meanes, and then liuing, <hi>Nulla mora interpoſita ad Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Bohemiae Lodouicum inaugurandum curauit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dubrau. p. <hi>302.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lodoui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:21929:13"/>is drowned in the Danuby in the Rowt giuen by the Turkes, and leaues his onely ſiſter <hi>Anne</hi> married to <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Emperor, who, as <hi>Dubrauius</hi> ſayes, could not bee preuented by ſlight,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> nor wit, nor Armes, <hi>Dextra prorſus manus &amp; tenaci exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit gubernacula regni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all theſe times there is no Succeſſion eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, but free Election, or another reaſon of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion then right. Princes choſen of the younger line, reiecting the Elder, and the right line, and ſome few ſeizures by force, Princes depoſed for miſgouernment, and for vvant of due forme in the Election: Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in bloud Elected, and all pretended ſucceſſion, aduanced by the Father liuing, or for his ſake dead; and this concludes no ſucceſſion, becauſe preſent greatneſſe hath gotten an aduantage, <hi>Primus dominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ſpes in arduo, vbi ſis ingreſſus, addeſſe ſtudia, &amp; mixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtros.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tac. Annal. li. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ferdinand</hi> hath gotten poſſeſſion, but accepts it by right of Election, as is confeſſed, <hi>Nulla facta men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione Iuris quod Annae competebat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Informator. pag. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and giues Defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Letters, <hi>Quod ex nulla obligatione ſed ex libera &amp; bona voluntate eum Boemi eligerint</hi> againſt vvhich the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> now vrge a reſumption of thoſe letters, and a new declaration of the right of <hi>Anne:</hi> for the truth of which, there is no record in it own proper time and place, &amp; that which is, is crept into the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen, from which moſt corruptions into <hi>Claſsique</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors haue beene deriued. But admitte it vvere true, there is no ſtronger Argument againſt the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; For thereby <hi>Ferdinand</hi> doth confeſſe a prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and ſtretch of his authority for his aduantage
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21929:14"/>againſt a former confeſſed right. The acceptance of the Election without the right of <hi>Anne,</hi> was ſafer for him then to come in by her right, becauſe ſo hee was eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in his owne title, which might haue failed by the death of his wife, ſingly depending on her, and Kingdomes ſucceſſiue are not held in curteſie; But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ninteene yeares, hauing a ſetled poſterity by <hi>Anne,</hi> it was then for his aduantage in preiudice of the liberty of the States, to diſclayme the Election, and to claime by his wife for his childrens intereſt, who ſhould not then hazard a new Election, but ſucceed. And this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon cauſed the former Kings of <hi>Boheme</hi> to procure their ſonnes crowned when they could, and ſome as appears, could not. This practice diſcredits the whole claime, and is founded vpon <hi>Ferdinand</hi> intereſſed againſt <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinand</hi> freely elected.</p>
            <p>As farre as mine Authors haue led me, in mine owne purpoſe, which was to ſhew a continuall claime and practiſe in the States of Bohemia to Elect their Princes and Kings, I haue (perhaps with too much breuity) deliuered the ſame truth I found recorded, and I doubt not it will bee cleare enough to all well affected men, that my propoſitions are made euident in ſundry ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and ſo my Concluſion will ſtand, <hi>Bohemiae Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Electinum;</hi> but becauſe I profeſſed at firſt, that the <hi>Informator</hi> had miſ-vſed his ſtuffe to ſerue his owne ends, and to beguile the ſimplicity of our mindes, I ſtand bound not ſo to accuſe him, without ſhewing in ſome particulars, which way hee hath made that which was ſtraight crooked. The truth I haue deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as a Rule, will doe it; but vntill I haue alſo demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated his crookedneſſe, mine owne may lye vnder the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21929:14"/>ſame ſuſpition; where therefore his Vſes ſeem to croſſe my Narration, I will endeuour to ſhew the fallacy or peruerceneſſe;<note place="margin">Informator. pag. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Deſiring you to obſerue that the <hi>Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mator</hi> ſeemes to inſinuate, that this claime of <hi>Free Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> is fortified by Teſtimonies onely of ſixe Ages, which indeed were weake, although true, in reſpect of ſo many changes; but we ſay, that from the firſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling to this age, wee haue Right and Practice on our part without Interruption. Firſt hee denies euen that continuance of ſixe ages, by example of <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Luxen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> who as he pretends, had right to the Kingdome by marriage of his wife <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> heyre of the Crown. I will not confute him with any other reaſon then his owne. His next words are;<note place="margin">Inform. pag. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Indeed Henry of Carinthia married the elder ſiſter Anne,</hi> by which he tooke the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance of the Kingdom: How then could <hi>Iohn</hi> haue Right by the <hi>younger ſiſter?</hi> but hee tells vs <hi>Henry</hi> was depoſed by the Emperour, (we ſay by the people, and that they called in <hi>Iohn</hi>) but he tells not, who gaue the Emperour power to depoſe a King in Boheme: ye; he ſhowes the fault, becauſe he rebelled againſt the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour: And this <hi>Rebellion</hi> was, becauſe <hi>Henrie</hi> entred the Kingdome in his Wifes right, without demanding an Inveſtiture; If it were the right of <hi>Iohn,</hi> husband to the yonger ſiſter (as the <hi>Informator</hi> will haue it) how is it Rebellion in the Elder to clayme or defend that right? or what fault is it in them to take their own? if any had a right of ſueceſſion, and ſhould refuſe, for other quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels to demand the Inveſtiture, or the Emperor to grant it, can this vitiate the right, and make them no heyres? A right ſo limited is a miſerable Wardſhip; &amp; although the Emperours reſerued that honour of <hi>Inueſtiture,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21929:15"/>they gaue the title of King, yet they gaue not the right of being Prince, or being heyre: ſo that <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> could not for this cauſe be ſo a Rebell, as to bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled from all Soueraignty; and if not, then <hi>Iohn</hi> could as yet haue no right by <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> But admit it bee ſo, that <hi>Henry</hi> rebelled, could bee forfeit the right of his Wife? Or can ſucceſſiue kingdomes bee forfeited for want of Ceremony? Nothing is more abſurd. But what conſideration of their rights had the Emperour <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that thruſt both out, to place his ſons <hi>Rodolph</hi> and <hi>Fredericke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To vnfold all theſe Contradictions, we muſt returne to the truth of Story;<note place="margin">Theſe</note> neither of his ſiſters had, nor clai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med right: But the Bohemians (alwaies reſpectiue to the deſcendents of their Kings) firſt Elected the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band of <hi>Anne</hi> the eldeſt, and after reiecting him for miſgouernment, called in <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Luxenburgh;</hi> And though they gaue him <hi>Elizabeth</hi> to bee his Wife, they plainly choſe him for their King.</p>
            <p>Next he tells vs,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Wenceſlaus</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Charles,</hi> at three yeares of age was Crowned King by his Fathers Command, <hi>abſque vlla requiſitione ſtatuum:</hi> That ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue is not proued, and I aske no more Inference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, and that which it concludes, <hi>quod Iure ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis,</hi> then his owne words, <hi>his Father commanded it,</hi> which if you make gentler, and ſay (as the truth is) he deſired it wee are agreed; for to command it, if he had right, was vnneceſſary, to entreat and procure it, not ſo, hauing no right.</p>
            <p>I omit his boldneſſe contrary to good authority,<note place="margin">Idem pag. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> to auerre that <hi>Albert</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> claymed the kingdome in right of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> when it is euident, that <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> at
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21929:15"/>his death preſented him to the States, by vehement words of recommendation; and the imputation caſt vpon the Aſhes of <hi>Podiebrad</hi> (whom indeed hee hates, for againſt his Election ſtands no exception) and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend to the onely clayme, that the daughters were true heyres; to proue which he auerrs, that <hi>Caſsimir</hi> of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land pretended right to the Kingdome at the Election of <hi>Podiebrad,</hi> which is vtterly falſe; and that <hi>Podiebrad</hi> preuailed by a faction of a few, againſt the more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull of the States, which is in it ſelfe abſurd, &amp; brands <hi>Pope Calixtus</hi> his approbation; for neuer was any King choſen with more vniuerſal applauſe. But admit all that true, the Concluſion to be proued is, <hi>That the Kingdome did deſcend in right to a Daughter;</hi> and ſo after <hi>Podiebrad,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Caſsimir</hi> was admitted; to vſe his owne words, The kingdome did returne to the ordinary ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, <hi>de Iure,</hi> was it ordinary that the younger did ſucceed? Was not <hi>Anne</hi> married to the Duke of <hi>Saxe,</hi> the Elder, and heyre, if there were a right of Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Was <hi>Anne</hi> depoſed by any Emperour, or any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree againſt her? if not, what clayme had the ſonne of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> againſt his Aunt and her iſſue? And how, by the right and vigour of their priuiledges did the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome appertaine to the younger in bloud? But we ſee theſe daughters Titles <hi>pieced up</hi> to confirme the claime of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> by <hi>Anne</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Ladiſlaus,</hi> which hee at his owne Election durſt not truſt vnto.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, he preferres to vs the Letters or Bulls of <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke, Charles, Ferdinand,</hi> and <hi>Vladiſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> to entaile the Kingdome to the Princes of the bloud, but none of theſe to the next in bloud, which formes a ſucceſſion, but at large, that any of the bloud may be choſen, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21929:16"/>to that of greateſt force, which ſeemes excluſiue (when none of the bloud ſhall remaine) the words following are, <hi>or by any other meanes when the Crowne ſhall bee voyd,</hi> which muſt needs be by death of any in poſſeſſion: But we ſay that in the golden Bull of <hi>Charles,</hi> he not onely excepts his Kingdom of Bohemia, and the right of the States to chooſe their King <hi>whomſoeuer they will,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Onaph. Aurea Bulla <hi>431.</hi>
               </note> in any vacancy, but alſo confirmes that right ſo, that no <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, Regall</hi> nor <hi>Imperiall,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aurea Bulla pag. <hi>481.</hi>
               </note> ſhall bee of force againſt it; and this, in words direct and vehement. So that whatſoeuer could follow for the aduantage of any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Houſe, could not preiudice an Ancient and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Right of a whole Kingdome, and the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice hereof is the ſafeſt and beſt Interpretor. I haue preſented the <hi>Truth</hi> naked and ſimply; If it do any man ſeruice, I am glad; if not, I am glad that I haue learned it for my ſelfe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21929:16"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21929:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
